MINGZE WANG

210, Jingyuan Building #6, Peking University, Beijing, China, 100084 mingzewang@stu.pku.edu.cn

SHORT BIO

I am a third-year Ph.D candidate in Computational Mathematics, Peking University. I am very fortunate to be advised by Prof. Weinan E. Prior to that, I received my B.S. degree in Pure and Applied Mathematics (ranking 1/111 for the first three years during my undergraduate study) from Zhejiang University in 2021. My homepage is https://wmz9.github.io/.

EDUCATION

Peking University

Beijing, China

Ph.D Candidate, Computational Mathematics

2021.09 - Present

School of Mathematical Sciences

Advisor: Prof. Weinan E.

Zhejiang University

Hangzhou, China 2017.09 - 2021.06

Bachelor of Science, Pure and Applied Mathematics

School of Mathematical Sciences

Academic ranking: 1/111, Comprehensive ranking: 1/111, Major GPA: 4.84/5 (95.5/100).

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am broadly interested in theory, algorithm and application of machine learning. I am also interested in non-convex and convex optimization. Recently, I am also dedicated to use theory to design algorithms elegantly. Specifically, my recent research topics are

- Deep learning theory: theory and theory-inspired algorithm [1][2][3][4][5][6][8][9][10]
 - **Expressivity**: Explore the expressive power of Transformers through the lens of approximation theory [9]; the expressivity of state-space models.
 - **Optimization**: Why can optimization algorithms converge to global minima when training neural networks [2][4]?
 - **Implicit Bias**: Why can optimization algorithms converge to global minima with favorable generalization ability when training neural networks? Flat-minima-bias [3][5][10]; max-margin-bias aspects [4][6].
 - Generalization: How to measure the generalization ability of neural networks [1].
 - Algorithm Design: For machine learning problems, design new optimization algorithms which can (i) converge faster [10]; (ii) generalize better [6][10].
- Transformer and Large Language Models: theory and algorithm. [9][10]
 - **Expressivity**: The expressive power and mechanisms of Transformer [9]; the mechanisms of in-context learning; the expressivity of state-space models.
 - **Algorithm Design:** Design faster optimizers for training LLMs [10]; design more efficient model architectures; design more efficient strategy for data selection.
- Non-convex and Convex Optimization: theory and algorithm. [2][4][6][10]
 - Convex Optimization in ML. [6]
 - Non-convex Optimization in ML. [2][4][10]
 - Algorithm Design: Design faster optimizers for training neural networks [10]; accelerate the convergence for the problems with specific structure [6].
- Computer vision and Natural language processing: algorithm and application [7].

PUBLICATIONS & PREPRINTS

- 10. Mingze Wang, Haotian He, Jinbo Wang, Zilin Wang, Guanhua Huang, Feiyu Xiong, Zhiyu Li, Weinan E, Lei Wu. Improving Generalization and Convergence by Enhancing Implicit Regularization. Under review. arXiv preprint: 2405.20763, 1-35. 2024.
- 9. Mingze Wang, Weinan E. Understanding the Expressive Power and Mechanisms of Transformer for Sequence Modeling. Under review. arXiv preprint: 2402.00522, 1-70. 2024.
- 8. Liu Ziyin, Mingze Wang, Hongchao Li, Lei Wu. Loss Symmetry and Noise Equilibrium of Stochastic Gradient Descent. Under review. arXiv preprint: 2402.07193, 1-26, 2024.
- 7. Guanhua Huang, Yuchen Zhang, Zhe Li, Yongjian You, Mingze Wang, Zhouwang Yang. Are Al-Generated Text Detectors Robust to Adversarial Perturbations? Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, (ACL 2024), 1-20. 2024.
- 6. Mingze Wang, Zeping Min, Lei Wu. Achieving Margin Maximization Exponentially Fast via Progressive Norm Rescaling. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2024), 1-38. 2023.
- 5. Mingze Wang, Lei Wu. A Theoretical Analysis of Noise Geometry in Stochastic Gradient Descent. NeurIPS 2023 Workshop on Mathematics of Modern Machine Learning (NeurIPS 2023 Workshop M3L). arXiv preprint: 2310.00692, 1-30. 2023.
- 4. Mingze Wang, Chao Ma. Understanding Multi-phase Optimization Dynamics and Rich Nonlinear Behaviors of ReLU Networks. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2023, Spotlight (Top 3.5%)), 1-94. 2023.
- 3. Lei Wu, Mingze Wang, Weijie J. Su. The alignment property of SGD noise and how it helps select flat minima: A stability analysis. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2022), 1-25. 2022.
- 2. Mingze Wang, Chao Ma. Early Stage Convergence and Global Convergence of Training Mildly Parameterized Neural Networks. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2022), 1-73. 2022.
- 1. Mingze Wang, Chao Ma. Generalization Error Bounds for Deep Neural Networks Trained by **SGD.** Under review. arXiv preprint: 2206.03299, 1-32. 2022.

SERVICE

Conference: Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS); International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR).

Journal: Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR); Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI); Pattern Recognition (PR); Transactions on Machine Learning Research (TMLR); Journal of Machine Learning (JML).

EXPERIENCE

Peking University Beijing, China

Teaching assistant: Deep Learning Theory, taught by Prof. Zhiyuan Li (TTIC) Summer School 2023.

Teaching assistant: Calculus (A) Fall 2021

Teaching assistant: Calculus (B) Fall 2022, 2023; Spring 2022, 2023, 2024

Institute for Advanced Algorithms Research

Shanghai, China Algorithm Intern 2023.12 - now

Work on designing faster optimizers for pretraining large language models.

Moqi Technology Beijing, China

2021.09 - 2022.06 Algorithm Intern

SELECTED AWARDS & HONOURS

Principal Scholarship, Peking University.	2024.05
BICMR Mathematical Award for Graduate Students (110,000 RMB), Peking University.	2023.11
Schlumberge Scholarship (30,000 RMB), Peking University.	2022.10
PKU Academic Innovation Award (top 1%), Peking University.	2022.10
Outstanding Graduate of Zhejiang Province (top 5%); Outstanding Graduate of ZJU	2021.05
Chinese National Scholarship (top 1%)	2019.10
First Class Scholarship of ZJU (top 3%)	2019, 2020.10
Zhejiang Provincial Government Scholarship	2018.10
First Prize of Mathematical Contest in Modeling of ZJU (top 1%)	2020.06
Meritourious Award in The Mathematical Contest in Modeling	2020.02
National Second Prize of Chinese Undergraduate Mathematical Contest in Modeling (top 2.5%)	2019.10